Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II. Films on Organized Labor and the Political Left, 1925-2005; 19.5 Linear Feet in 13 record cartons, 31 film cans, 1 cassette box, 1 manuscript box, and 1 card box
  - The Challenge, 1951 (Film canister c225, 16mm film reels 001_0762, Film canister c222, 16mm film reels 001_0763)
    The film is a dramatization of the Report of the President's Committee on Civil Rights. It features a combination of fictional stories and scripted interviews with a number of public figures playing themselves. People interviewed include: Reverend Henry Knox Sherril, presiding bishop of the Episcopal Church and head of the National Council of Churches of Christ; H.E. Steinkrauss, former head of the National Chamber of Commerce; (23:00) Philip Murray, president of the CIO; and (25:23) William Green, president of the AFL. The film was distributed by the Freedom Film Library of the Metropolitan New York Regional Office Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, Forum Films, and The March of Time.
  - The Cord Over the Abyss, 1954 (Film canister c224, 16mm film reels 001_0766)
    Dramatic film about a conservative young woman's conflict with her progressive parents. Presented by CBS Television in cooperation with the American Jewish Tercentenary Committee.
  - The Burden of Truth, circa 1957 (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0908, Film canister c220, 16mm film reels 001_0895)
    Dramatised film depicting a steel worker's life and experiences of racial prejudice. Produced for the United Steelworkers of America Committee on Civil Rights.
  - Don't Be A Sucker, circa 1957 (Box 18, Film canister c204, 16mm film reels 001_0359)
    Dramatized film on the subject of bigotry, ethnic prejudice and xenophobia. Its two main characters are a young American-born man and a new American citizen, an older man who is a professor and recent emigre from Hungary.
  - The Golden Door, circa 1957 (Film canister c203, 16mm film reels 001_0222)
    Animated pro-immigration film with voiceover sound and narration reviews history of immigration restrictions in the United States, immigration laws at the date film was made, and makes recommendation on United States immigration policy.
  - AFL-CIO Committee for Political Education Promotional Film, circa 1960 (Box 18, Film canister c172, 16mm film reels 001_0363)
    A promotional film for COPE (the AFL-CIO's Committee for Political Education). Among the issues discussed are: the increasing participation of big business in election of candidates, subversion of the original purpose of government agencies regulating labor, such as the National Labor Relations Board, right-to-work laws and other restrictive labor legislation, automation, runaway plants, low voter turnout, the desirability of a federal civil rights law, crisis in the school system, and high medical costs.
  - Democracy Against the Hate Mongers, 1960 (Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0446)
    A Vision Association Production presented by Frank Ross and Mervyn LeRoy; Writer: Albert Maltz; Musical Director: Axel Stordahl; Director of Photography: Robert de Grass(o?); Song: "The House I Live In" - Music by Earl Robinson, words by Lewis Allan.
  - John F. Kennedy Campaign Film, 1960
    Campaign film for John F. Kennedy for the presidential campaign of 1960. It reviews his public career (World War II, his race for the United States Senate and service in the Senate), shows him posed with the books he wrote; it shows him campaigning for president--shaking hands with voters, including working people (coal miners wearing head lamps). Stock footage, including President Dwight Eisenhower with Nikita Khrushchev.
    - Film (Box 16, Film canister c121, 16mm film reels 001_0394)
    - Soundtrack (Box 16, Film canister c121, 16mm film reels 001_0395)
  - The Extremists, circa 1964 (Film canister c171, 16mm film reels 001_0064, Film canister c126, 16mm film reels 001_0258)
    Advocacy film warning against extremist political groups. Ends with an appeal to viewers to support the AFL-CIO's Committee on Political Education (COPE).
  - Do It: Organizing a Local Union COPE Committee, circa 1965-1975 (Film canister c162, 16mm film reels 001_0182)
    Instructional film on how to organize a local union COPE (the AFL-CIO's Committee on Political Education). Includes introductory look at COPE, and its importance. Emphasizes COPE's responsibility to get union members to register to vote, to inform members on political issues, and to solicit and collect contributions to COPE.
  - Tomorrow is Another Day: History of the SIU, circa 1965-1975 (Film canister c192, 16mm film reels 001_0435)
    A documentary history of seafarers in the United States, from colonial times to present, and of the Seafarers International Union of North America.
  - Warsaw Ghetto: Holocaust and Resistance, 1974
    Narrated by Theodore Bikel; Produced by the Jewish Labor Committee.
    - Audio (Box 8, Audiocassette 001_0710)
    - Film (Box 8, 35mm film reels 001_0711)
  - United Steel Workers Great Copper Strike, 1967-1968 (Film canister c118, 16mm film reels 001_0243)
    Includes segment on President Curran
  - The Phony Issue --The Real Issues and You, 1976 (Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0445)
    Documentary that contrasts the real political issues (as seen by the AFL-CIO) of unemployment, healthcare, inflation, and tax justice with the false political issue of "Big Government" raised by conservatives. It reviews the history of blaming "Big Government" as a way to evade the real issues mentioned above, beginning in 1964 with the presidential campaign of Republican Barry Goldwater; it urges election of good candidates to Congress and White House as antidote to the nation's problems and advocates union members working through COPE (AFL-CIO's Committee for Political Education) to help accomplish this. Details COPE's programs and strategies.
  - Right-Wing Machine, 1977 (Box 27, 16mm film reels 001_0907)
    Combination of animation and live-action film. Issues examined are the "new right's" use of a powerful combination of technology, direct mail, and "manpower" to reach its goals.
  - CIA and the Press, 1982 (Film canister c245, 16mm film reels cuid8219)
  - AFSCME Contracting Out, Burn-in, January 11, 1988 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0532)
    Does not rewind properly
  - Local 237 Founders Day, June, 1998 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0531)
  - For a Liveable Future, 1988 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0534)
    Excerpts from a conversation between Willa Kenover, candidate for president of the Socialist Party USA, and Rob Lewis of the Austin local of the Socialist Party.
  - Labor Hall of Fame Honoree Video -- Mother Jones and Sidney Hillman, circa 1990 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0605)
  - Labor Hall of Fame 1990 Inductees (Box 11, Vhs 001_0604)
  - Proposal for Ceremony -- Moment of Sound, September 11, 2002 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0610, 001_0611)
  - "Thursday 'Till Nine Songs", November 22, 2002; cuid43063
    The performance took place on Friday, November 22, 2002 performance at Brooklyn College. Running time is under 60 minutes. The original performance of this musical was presented by the New York Department Store Joint Board, CIO on November 24, 25, 26, and 27, 1947, for the benefit of the Paralyzed Veterans Association of America. Book and lyrics were by Norman Franklin and Henry Foner and music by Norman Franklin.
  - "Sister Cities for Peace: Munich - New York City" Discussion with U.S. Peace Groups and WBAI Interview, May, 2005; cuid43065
  - "Stop EU Militarization" -- Munich Peace Conference, 2005; cuid43064
  - Cedric Belfrage Hollywood Interview VCA, Undated (Box 8, Vhs 001_0628)
  - Central America 9-12, Undated (Box 11, 8mm film reel 001_0729)
  - A Chance to Love, Undated (Box 11, 16mm film reels 001_0615, Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 24)
    The address label in Folder 24 was originally found within the film can.
  - Communication Workers of America Series -- Tape 47, Undated (Box 14, Betacam sp 001_0938)
  - Communication Workers of America Series -- Tape 49, Undated (Box 14, Betacam sp 001_0937)
  - Communication Workers of America Series -- Tape 50, Undated (Box 14, Betacam sp 001_0936)
  - End Conscription Campaign "Here and Now Show", Undated (Box 15, Vhs 001_0741)
    Including speaker Gavin Evans.
  - Freedom of Speech on Trial: Proof of NYPD False Charges Against Geoffrey Blank, Undated; cuid43066
  - "Hard Choices" by Daniel Kazimierski, Marion Lipschutz, Peggy Weiss, Undated (Box 15, U-matic 001_0745)
  - "Hidden Heroes: Youth Activism Today", Undated (Box 15, Vhs 001_0744)
    Produced by the Andrew Goodman Foundation
  - "If You Don't Come In On Sunday... Don't Come In On Monday", Undated (Box 15, Vhs 001_0739)
    Produced by the Manpower Education Institute
  - "In the Shadow of the Tower" U.A.W. Local 2300, Undated (Box 15, Vhs 001_0742)
  - Jewish Labor Committee -- Digital Air and Sound Restoration, Undated (Box Shared Tamiment 093, Dat 001_0708, 001_0709, Box Shared Tamiment 115, Disc TW_FILMS_001_1)
  - Jewish Labor Committee -- Negative Films, Undated (Box Shared Tamiment 132, 35mm film reels 001_0720, 001_0721, 001_0722, 001_0723)
    Optical negative: 001_0722, 001_0723; Duplicate negative: 001_0720, 001_0721.
  - Kramer 2, Undated (Box 11, Super 8mm film reel 001_0612)
  - La Parola 34th Anniversary, Undated (Film canister CT-6, 16mm film reels 001_0759)
  - Mexico - Central America 2-8, Undated (Box 11, 8mm film reel 001_0731)
  - New York Project, Undated
    - Episode 2 (Version A) (Box 11, Vhs 001_0603)
    - Episode 3 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0607)
    - Episode 4 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0608)
    - Episode 5 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0606)
  - Our Voices / Nuestras Voces, Undated; cuid43067
    NMASS Media Projects Presents: oral history documentaries made by, for, and about the residents and workers of the Lower East Side community.
  - PS216 Q Windows, Undated (Box 15, Vhs 001_0743)
    Unedited video of PS 216 window installation in Queens.
  - NYU / Tamiment: Traitor, Lindy Laub, Undated (Box Shared Tamiment 093, Minidv 001_0712, 001_0713, 001_0714, Box 8, Digital betacam 001_0734, 001_0735, 001_0736)
    Transfer from16mm film
  - The UFT Story, Undated (Box 5, Vhs 001_0496)
- Series III. Tamiment Library Event Recordings, 1979-2003; 6.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 cassette box, 1 flat box, and 1 manuscript box
  Series III. Tamiment Library Event Recordings (1979-2003) contains videos of events organized by Tamiment Library. These events include receptions for written publications by authors including Ron Jacobs, Zellig Harris, Paul LeBlanc, Frank Lovell, Scott McLemee, Alan Wald, JoAnn Wypijewski, and Jeremy Brecher; symposiums and discussions on the topics of poverty during the Clinton administration, being openly gay at work, academic labor, Trotskyism in the United States, and the Spanish Civil War, among others; and memorials for Phil Foner, Frank Lovell, Myra Tanner Weiss, and Cedric Belfrage. This series also includes flyers for the recorded events, and one poster for "Between Classes: A Conference on Academic Labor."
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Chamber of Commerce Conference, April 26, 1979 (Box 8, Half inch video reel 001_0539, 001_0540, 001_0541, 001_0542, 001_0543)
  - Cedric Belfrage and Jim Aronson re: Guardian, 1983 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0627)
  - Ft Point Dedication of Benches -- Lou Goldblatt, August 16, 1986 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0535)
    Lou Goldblatt was the founder of the ILW Cooperative at St. Francis Square and was involved in trade union housing.
  - Cedric Belfrage Original -- Memorial, 1990 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0625)
  - "1968 Revisited," John Ben Snow Room, Bobst Library, October 14, 1993 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0715, 001_0716, 001_0717)
    001_0716 and 001_0717 are unedited dubs.
  - "Saul Mills and the Greater New York Industrial Union Council CIO" Conference, Tamiment Library, April 7, 1992 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0536)
  - Harry Bridges Bust Ceremony, Conference on the Tradition of Dissent Among Waterfront Workers, January 28-29, 1994 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0533)
  - Phil Foner Memorial, February 5, 1995 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0619)
  - Greenwich House Opening, October 11, 1995 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0630)
  - "Between Classes: A Conference on Academic Labor," The Great Hall, D'Agostino Building, November 16, 1996 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0679, 001_0680, 001_0681)
  - "Between Classes: A Conference on Academic Labor" event poster, November 16, 1996 (Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 15)
  - Rand School Reunion, October, 1996 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0626)
  - Tamiment Library Event Flyers, 1996-1999 (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 25, 26)
  - Reception for "Trotskyism in the United States," Tamiment Library, March 29, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0676)
    Speakers include Paul LeBlanc, Frank Lovell, Scott McLemee, and Alan Wald.
  - Reception for "Survivor from a Dead Age: The Memoirs of Louis Lozowick", Tamiment Library, April 29, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0677)
    Special Guests include Virginia H. Marquardt and Adele Lozowick.
  - Reception for Michael Denning, Tamiment Library, September 23, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0675)
  - Reception for "The Transformation of Capitalist Society" by Zellig S. Harris, Tamiment Library, September 30, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0674)
  - Reception for Ron Jacobs, Tamiment Library, October 29, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0673)
  - Reception for Paul Robeson, Jr., Tamiment Library, November 5, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0687)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss Memorial, November 7, 1997 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0621, 001_0622)
  - Out at Work Symposium, NYU Cantor Film Center, November 15, 1997 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0684, 001_0685, 001_0686)
  - "A Celebration of Paul Robeson," Gallatin / Actors Equity, February 2, 1998 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0682, 001_0683)
  - "Culture and Poverty in the Clinton Era," a conversation with Linda Gordon and Katha Pollitt, Tamiment Library, February 10, 1998 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0688)
    Recording made by NYU TV
  - Israel at 50, Arthur Bernstein, Interview by Chronicle WBZTV, Mimi Wishner Segal and Jane Weinberg, April 1998 (Box 15, Vhs 001_0740)
  - Reception for "Painting by Numbers: Komar and Melanid's Scientific Guide to Art," Tamiment Library, April 1, 1998 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0689)
    Featuring JoAnn Wypijewski and Komar and Melamid.
  - Reception for Jeremy Brecher, Tamiment Library, April 30, 1998 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0690)
  - Frank Lovell Memorial, Tamiment Library, NYU, September 20, 1998 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0620, 001_0623, 001_0624)
  - "Just the Facts" Book Party, November 20, 1998 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0629)
  - "Red Diapers: Growing Up in the Communist Left" Reception, Tamiment Library, March 26, 1999
    - Audio (Box Shared Tamiment 093, Audiocassette 001_0707)
    - Video (Box 7, Vhs 001_0529)
  - Breitman / Lovell Opening, Tamiment Library, April 18, 1999 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0530)
  - Reception for New Editions of "Encyclopedia of American Left" and "Detroit: I Do Mind Dying", May 11, 1999 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0527)
  - John Poulos Collection Opening, Tamiment Library, May 14, 1999 (Box 7, Vhs 001_0528, Box 8, Vhs 001_0631)
  - A Tribute to Marty Glaberman, February 17, 2002 (Box 8, Vhs 001_0732)
    Produced by BMC Media
  - Alumni Association -- Ms. Melinda Holm, March 18, 2003 (Box 11, Vhs 001_0609)
  - Debra Bernhardt at Conference, Undated (Box 7, Vhs 001_0537, 001_0538)
    Includes footage from a conference on women and labor unions.
  - Marta Rey Garcia Lecture, King Juan Carlos Center, Undated (Box 7, Vhs 001_0678)
    Contains a lecture on the Spanish Civil War's impact in the United States.